<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr. Mead, in answer to several unscriptural, and unsound sayings of his in a sermon against the seventh-day-sabbath, preached at his place of meeting, the twenty third of the second month. 1682. Wrote the same day the sermon was preached, refuting his arguments, and turning them back, making their unskilfulness and weakness manifest; and clearly evidencing, that the seventh-day is the sabbath day; by clear scripture-testimony, and sound arguments grounded thereon. Published for his hearers, because he would neither hear an objection in publick, nor admit of a conference in private.</title>
            <author>Tovey, W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1957B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222359</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833540</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833540</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62992)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2067:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr. Mead, in answer to several unscriptural, and unsound sayings of his in a sermon against the seventh-day-sabbath, preached at his place of meeting, the twenty third of the second month. 1682. Wrote the same day the sermon was preached, refuting his arguments, and turning them back, making their unskilfulness and weakness manifest; and clearly evidencing, that the seventh-day is the sabbath day; by clear scripture-testimony, and sound arguments grounded thereon. Published for his hearers, because he would neither hear an objection in publick, nor admit of a conference in private.</title>
                  <author>Tovey, W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold by John Lawrence at the Angel in Cornhil, near the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W. Tovey.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With a postscript at the bottom of p. 16.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> MEAD, IN ANSWER to ſeveral Unſcriptural, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Sayings of his, in a Sermon againſt the Seventh-Day-Sabbath, Preached at his Place of Meeting, the <hi>Twenty Third</hi> of the <hi>Second</hi> Month. 1682.</p>
            <p>WROTE the ſame Day the Sermon was Preached, refuting his Arguments, and turning them back, making their Unskilfulneſs and Weakneſs manifeſt; and clearly Evidencing, That the <hi>Seventh-Day</hi> is the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day;</hi> by clear Scripture-Teſtimony, and ſound Arguments grounded thereon.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for his Hearers, becauſe he would neither hear an Objection in Publick, nor admit of a Conference in Private.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 27. 5.</bibl>
Open Rebuke is better than ſecret Love.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal-Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:38017:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38017:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Prefatory Epiſtle</hi> TO Mr. Meads Hearers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Brethren, and Fathers;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AND all you that heard him that day, Read the Defence which I make for my ſelf in this Practiſe; you are my Witneſſes (eſpecially ſuch of you as were near me) how I behaved my ſelf in your Aſſembly, giving no diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, or cauſe of offence to any Man; but liſtening attentively to the Word ſpoken, leſt I ſhould let any of it ſlip: And when the Sermon was ended, I ſtood up and aſſayed to ſpeak; but a Pſalm being called, I abode in ſilence until the whole Service was over; and then I ſtood up, and Meekly, Reverently, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively craved leave to ſpeak; to which Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> anſwered, That I had no Call to ſpeak there. And I replyed, He would better judge of that when he had heard what I had to ſay; (for he knew not but I might Report that God was in you of a Truth, <hi>1 Cor. 14. 25.</hi>) but I was again repulſed, and denyed leave to ſpeak: Wherefore I went away peaceably, neither with Noiſe or Tumult. And as I went forth, ſeveral of you witneſſed, That I ſpake mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, and wiſhed that I had been heard; and others of you gave me aſſurance, That Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> would be ready, and free to have private Conference with me, and urged me to take a convenient Seaſon to go to him; upon which I haſted home, and the ſame Afternoon wrote a large Letter to him; and I have Printed my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38017:3"/>
Letter herewith, that you may judge betwixt us: For receiving no Anſwer to my Letter, neither in publick (for he omitted Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the next Firſt-Day) nor in private: I took a Friend with me, and went to his Houſe, and told him, I was the Man, that in his publick Aſſembly, deſired leave to ſpeak; and had ſince Wrote unto him, and receiving no Anſwer to my Letter, I made bold to wait upon him for it: At which he Majeſterially asked me as the Chief Prieſt asked our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>By what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority I ſpake in his Meeting?</hi> At which I wonderingly repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his words—<hi>And he replyed (demandingly) Ay, I ask you by what Authority?</hi> And ſaid farther, <hi>That I made a Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in the Worſhip of God, and occaſioned a Scandal to be caſt upon them.</hi> To which I mildly anſwered, That I made no Diſturbance in the Worſhip of God; neither gave any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Scandal; and that I ſpake by the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and pulled out my Bible, to ſhew from the Scriptures, that my Practiſe therein was to be juſtified: But he not caring to have an Authentical Anſwer to <hi>His Majeſterial Demand,</hi> Pilate <hi>like,</hi> John 18. 38. <hi>went off from that, and told me, I had Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Abuſed him in my Letter, calling him ignorant Fellow, and asking him if he were not aſhamed.</hi> To which I anſwered, That I did not call him ignorant fellow; but to ſay he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this or that, I thought no crime, and hoped he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his ignorance in ſome things (and indeed ignorance is the faireſt excuſe that can be made for him) and I hope he would be aſhamed of an Error; and I wondered that he ſhould ſo Treat me: but he ſaid, he had ſhewn my Letter to my Betters and his too; and that he had a ſufficient account of me, what a fellow I was; inſinuating, as if he had heard ſome ill thing of me, but mentioning nothing; but I knew, he that reproved a Scorner, would get to himſelf a Blot: And I urged to have an Anſwer to my Arguments, but he ignorantly told me, I deſerved no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but to be ſent to the Houſe of Correction; and he could ſpend his time better, than to talk with ſuch a fellow; and ſo he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me the way to the Door. And more ſuch like words he gave me, though I gave him no one provoking word, but Debaſed my ſelf to Gain upon him; becauſe I had heard he was a <hi>Proud High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Man.</hi> When he ſaid I deſerved to be ſent to the Houſe of Correction, I anſwered him, That I was glad he had not Power: And ſo I am, for if he had power, I might have a <hi>Scandalum Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38017:3"/>
brought againſt me, of more Hundred Pounds Damage, than I am worth, though the Letter was privately ſent to his own hand, and he ſuffered no damage at all. It may be, ſome of you will not know how to bear my Plain-dealing with the Man you ſo much Love; but how do you think I can bear, being threatned with a Houſe of Correction, a place for vagrant Rogues, and not for a Man that is well known, and lives in good Repute, whoſe Wife, and Children, and Servants, are all an Honour to him? How do you think ſuch a Man can bear ſuch Majeſterial Threats, from one that hath no power over him? and how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking was it to be deſpiſed and ſcorned, as not worthy to be ſpoke to; and how unlike humble <hi>Paul</hi> was it to carry it thus? for <hi>Paul</hi> became all things to all Men, that he might by any means Save ſome. If any of you do judge my Stile too harſh, I deſire you will weigh his Carriage to me in the ſame Ballance; and for what was ſuggeſted againſt me, I told him it was a light thing with me, to be Judged of Mans Judgement; but let them that Accuſe me, ſpeak nothing but the truth, and I challenge them to ſearch my whole Life, and publiſh my Crimes, if they themſelves be not guilty of them: through Mercy I have been kept from the common Pollutions of the Times, and Corruptions in my Calling, fraudulent Dealing, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury; and of this I have Witneſs: And I am ſure the worſt he could hear of me, was, that I am a Paſſionate Man; Ay, I am perſwaded, that was the account he had of me; for he took a ready courſe to be too hard for a Collerick Man; but he did not magnify his Office therein. I do not glory in my Paſſion, or count it a light Sin, but write it to my <hi>ſhame,</hi> that he may not think I exalt my ſelf above him, when I would have him be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of any Error he committed; and if an Enemy will diſcover any Sin in me, that I do not ſee in my ſelf, I will count him my Friend therein: Nay, though he do it out of Mallice, I will accept it in Love; and if I ſhall get the farther Knowledge of Sin in my ſelf (by this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy) ſo that I may overcome it, I ſhall count I have good Gain; but if I can alſo convince him and you of the Error in his Doctrine, which I write againſt, I ſhall gain that I Labour for: Though what I have ſaid in haſt, be very ſhort of what might be pleaded for the Truth; yet if fudes be laid aſide, and a Conference be admitted in a calm cool Spirit, I doubt not, but to Anſwer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Objecter hath to ſay againſt the Truth and Duty I pleaded
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38017:4"/>
for: But if inſtead of that, Sin be added to Sin, and I am ſlanderouſly reported, and ſcandals be raiſed of me, which for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, are not true, and need to be anſwered, you muſt not expect that I can print books to clear my ſelf. No, that will be too coſtly. The cheapeſt way I can think of at preſent, is, to publiſh my Defence (if I am wronged) in ſome of the News books: And there you may expect to hear of me, on any ſuch Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. T:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38017:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER to Mr. <hi>MEAD,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Leave I Craved, with humble ſubmiſſion, in your publick Aſſembly this day, being not granted; I have wrote ſome of thoſe Objections I had then to make <hi>Ex Tempore,</hi> againſt the greateſt part of your Sermon, which you delivered premeditately, and with the help of Notes. And though I am but a Youth in Years, and of mean Capacity, whereby I am much your Inferior and Unequal; yet I hope through Grace, I am a Babe in Chriſt, having a Spiritual Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, whereby I can in ſome good meaſure diſcern the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Milk of the Word, from the unſavory ſayings of men without, and againſt the word of truth: And from thence it is I am Emboldened to ingage in this Controverſie with you: And before I ingage in the Refuting your Arguments againſt the Lords Honourable-Seventh-day-Sabbath, I firſt aſſure you, that I will endeavour to keep as cloſe as I can, to the exact form and due order of your Arguments; and if in any thing I miſs it, if you will make it known to me in writing, I will admit that to be your mind and meaning, which you ſhall ſo declare to me in writing to be your meaning. And that you may not miſtake me, I declare to you, that it is not any Argument againſt the God-head, or againſt the Power of Chriſt, that I do oppoſe: for I do firmly believe, The Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be God, Equal with the Father; that he is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and the Holy Spirit is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, one <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah.</hi> But my Objections are againſt your Aſſertion, That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt has Changed the day of the Sabbath; And that it was neceſſary he ſhould ſo do. Your Scriptures for it, you ſaid, you laid down the day before; and I not being preſent then, do not know them, and ſo cannot Anſwer to them: but thoſe Texts of Scripture, which have uſually been brought againſt it by Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and other Objectors againſt the Lords Honourable day, are largely diſcourſed, and their Genuine ſenſe and proper meaning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38017:5"/>
are held forth, and cleared up (agreeing with the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture where it Treats of that Subject matter) in a Treatiſe of the Sabbath, wrote by Mr. <hi>F. Bampfield,</hi> ſold by Mr. <hi>Lawrence</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> Your humane Authorities, which you brought to back your other plea, have no Authority with me, neither ought they to have any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the conſcience of any man, being contrary to Chriſt, and the word of Chriſt, and contradicting of one another. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> your firſt Author, ſaith they aſſembled on the <hi>Sunday;</hi> and gives this as the ground of it, That being the firſt day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God ſeparating the light from the darkneſs, did Create the World, And Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour roſe again from the dead: This is the ground of their Aſſembling, and both groundleſs. For the world was not made in a day, but in Six days, and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth was Created a Sabbath, and Sanctified a Sabbath; and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Fourth Command, being <hi>future Piel,</hi> he ſhall Sanctifie; does clearly prove the Continuance of its Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiedneſs: for it is ſtill a ſpeaking word, the like you have in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> concerning the light, (which your Author would make a wrong uſe of) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there ſhall be light, and there ſhall be light; the Word not only gave light a being, but continues it in its being; ſo this Word not only Sanctified the Sabbath, but continues it Sanctified as long as the word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Command; what, becauſe <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and the people with him, voluntarily met on that day, and gives a groundleſs reaſon for it, will you from thence Embolden your hearers to Tranſgreſs the Seventh-day-Sabbath? which ſin, the Lord hath Threatned ſo many Judgments againſt; and which fin you can hardly, prove your Author Guilty of: for although they met upon <hi>Sunday,</hi> and obſerved ſeveral other Feſtivals, with as great Veneration, and impoſed them with as great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, even <hi>Eaſter</hi> day, and all the fifty days from <hi>Eaſter</hi> to <hi>Whitſuntide,</hi> were accounted Holy; and Solemnized with no leſs obſervation than the <hi>Sundays</hi> were. Thus the Church was Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, with the obſervation of <hi>Holy-days</hi> ſo early, and with divers other Superſtitions, as Mixing water with the Wine in the Lords Supper, and ſtanding in their devotion, making Kneeling, which is the proper poſture in prayer, to be a crime in thoſe <hi>Holy-days,</hi> with many other Corruptions; and muſt the practiſe of ſuch a corrupt generation of Churches be brought
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38017:5"/>
forth; for a Confirmation of a Doctrine in this age, of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light; No, its too late to impoſe upon us with ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities. Yet your own Authors, call no other day the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath but the Seventh; nor for a thouſand years after Chriſt, were Hiſtorians ſo bold to call any other day by that name, or give that day any other name, and very many Churches did obſerve the Seventh-day-Sabbath, as your Hiſtorians mention; and one main difference between the <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, was that the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, faſted and afflicted themſelves on the Sabbath, which being no proper work on a Sabbath day, the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches admoniſhed them to reform it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they obſerve <hi>Sunday</hi> as a Sabbath, but did their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon buſineſs thereon, when their Aſſembling was over; neither did they pretend any Scripture ground, for their meeting on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> but took it up Voluntarily: and afterwards when it came to be confirmed by Edicts of men, even then much work was allowed to be done upon it, and the Seventh-day-Sabbath was not made void, but obedience required to that alſo; but I am a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this. How contrary to the word of God in your own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was the ſentence of the venerable Counſel of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> that you even now, when your firſt day is at the height, durſt not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it; but the Churches were corrupted in the Apoſtles time, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was then already come, and therefore we need not run to the Church Hiſtory, to find Errors in them, for which we ſhould not take them for a rule, ſince we are not referred to them, but to the Law, and to the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>But you come to Arguments, to prove that Chriſtians are not tied to the obſervation of the Seventh day-Sabbath; though tied to the obſervation of the Fourth Command (a plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in its ſelf) and one of your Arguments, which you call unanſwerable, is.</p>
            <p>That believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> or Chriſtians, are not bound to the obſervation of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, neither by the Law of Nature, nor by the Law of Moſes, nor by the Law of Chriſt; and becauſe this is the great Argument you reſt upon, and truſt in, I ſhall firſt put you in mind of ſome of your own Conceſſions; and then ſpeak directly to your Argument, as you inforced it.</p>
            <p>You grant that believers are bound, to the obſervation of the Ten Commands as a Rule of Life, (and I hope you will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38017:6"/>
grant as a Rule of Faith, and Worſhip too; or elſe you will leave out the greateſt Commandment) you alſo grant, that Law can no more be Changed, then the nature of good and evil can be Changed; that its the Expreſs <hi>Idea</hi> of Gods image; and that God can as ſoon ceaſe to be, as the Law to be Changed; that what is of Moral Equity, Extends to every believer or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man. Although you diſowned all that was in the Fourth Command to be Moral, yet you owned theſe three things Moral: as Firſt, the Obſervation of a Sabbath. Secondly, that this Sabbath is a Seventh part of time. Thirdly, that this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part of time muſt be of Gods own appointing; and as Corrupt as you are, in your opinion about the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; either through ignorance of the proper Significancy, and Genuine meaning of the Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (or worſe then igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) yet you have granted ſo much Truth, that you cannot deny the Seventh day to be the Sabbath, without contradicting your own words; for Sabbath-day and Seventh-day are conna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, it) is the Seventh-days proper nature, to be the week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sabbath, and that I will evidence to you, if you will appoint time and place; and the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are Notes of demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration pointing out a certain, known, determined, fixed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable Day in every week, and not a Seventh part of time barely; but that ſet Seventh day. And the Lord hath never appointed another day, which you grant muſt be of the Lords appointing; and when you ſpake, that Chriſt hath power to change the Sabbath, as he is God, do you not tremble to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon your hearers, with ſuch devices? Did you not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, God could as ſoon ceaſe to be, as the Law of the Ten words to be changed? your unskilful defining of the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhall not help you out in this caſe, as I will ſhew you preſently; therefore I now come to anſwer your ſuppoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Argument in its Three parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſaid believers are not bound to the obſervation of the Seventh day Sabbath, by the Law of nature, becauſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the light of nature can't diſcern the Seventh day, from any other, for there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between one day and another in nature: take a man and ſhut him up in a dungeon a conſiderable time; where he can ſee no light, and when he comes forth, he cannot know the Seventh day from any of the other days, and becauſe the Seventh day cannot be known by the Light of the nature, it is not of the Law of nature.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38017:6"/>
With a great many more of ſuch like words, (by the way I would tell you, that exact Aſtronomers have obſerved, that natural days are not of Equal Length, and it were worth your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch into it; whether the Seventh day be not longer in time, and have more minutes in it then the firſt.)</p>
            <p>But for anſwer to your Argument, if no Law be a Law of nature, but that which may be known by the Light of nature; then the firſt Command cannot be a Law of nature; for by the Light of nature we cannot come at the knowledge of the True God, of a God in Chriſt; neither by that Rule, is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Command a Law of nature, for by the Light of nature (as it is depraved by the fall) man knows not, that an after God is not to be worſhiped; but the Heathen and Pagans, that have not the Light of the written word, nor of the Enlightning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they worſhip after Gods. Neither can the Third Command be a Law of nature by that Rule; for by the Light of nature men know not that great and dreadful name <hi>Jehovah, AElohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> which is not to be taken in vain; neither can that part of the Fourth Command, which you acknowledge to be Moral, a Seventh part of time, be a Law of nature by that Rule, (for to uſe your own dark demonſtration) ſhut a man up in a Dungeon all his days; where he can ſee no Light; and the Light of nature, will not teach him the knowledge of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part of time; <hi>No,</hi> he muſt be taught by the Word, which is the ground of knowledge; how to number Seven, and how to meaſure the days, by the Luminaries of heaven: Neither can the Fifth Command, be a Law of nature by that Rule; for take a Child from his Parents before it knows them, as the <hi>Turks</hi> do, and breed it up where they ſhant know of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and call it by another name, and it cannot know its Parents to Honor them: Neither can the Sixth Command be a Law of nature by that Rule, for you know, you ſaid if it were a Law of nature, natural Conſcience would Check for the breach of it; but unbelieving men that have not faith, they have killed, and will kill the Saints, and think they do God good ſervice in it, they are ſo far from the Checks of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For ſhame retract this ignorant definition of the Law of nature. But to Anſwer your ſecond part of your ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary unanſwerable Argument.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38017:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Your ſecond part of your Argument was, <hi>That Believers are not bound to obſerve the Seventh-Day-Sabbath, by the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>or the Law, as given forth by</hi> Moſes, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>was given only to the</hi> Jews; <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Believers were freed from the whole Law, as given by</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>and muſt receive it as renewed by the Power of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How is that? Dare you ſay again as you did, <hi>That we are freed from the Law, as given at</hi> Sinai? Did not <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah Chriſt</hi> give the Law at <hi>Sinai? Pſal.</hi> 68. 17, 18. Did not the whole Earth quake at his Preſence and Voice? <hi>ver. 7, 8. Heb. 12. 25, 26. Eph.</hi> 4. 8. Is not this Chriſt the Angel that was with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> who then ſpake to him in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> received the lively Oracles to give unto us? <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 37, 38. And will you reject this Law, as given at <hi>Sinai,</hi> becauſe it was handed to us by <hi>Moſes?</hi> Is not this Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be remembred in the Laſt Days? <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 4. and the Context. Unleſs Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be imputed to you for your Juſtification, <hi>Moſes</hi> will accuſe you to the Father, <hi>John</hi> 5. 45. Had the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> believingly heard <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> they would have believed Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 46. If you will not believe <hi>Moſes</hi> his Writings, how can you believe Chriſt? I know not how you will Evidence your Faith in Chriſt, but by your Obedience to this Law of <hi>Moſes, James</hi> 2. 18. eſpecially.</p>
            <p>Will you not hear <hi>Moſes?</hi> then you are not of the mind of Glorified <hi>Abraham, Luk.</hi> 16. 29. Will you not hear <hi>Moſes?</hi> then you will not be perſwaded, though one Roſe from the Dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The third part of your Argument was, <hi>That Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are not tyed by the Law of Chriſt, to obſerve the</hi> Seventh-Day-Sabbath; <hi>for Chriſt never Re-inforced this Law; and the Apoſtle, who ſpake by Command from Chriſt, leaves Men to their Liberty, whether to obſerve it or not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How unskilfully do you divide the Word of God? Have I not proved in my laſt Anſwer, that Chriſt gave the Law at <hi>Sinai?</hi> And is not that the Law of Chriſt? And of unchangeable Nature? And does not that Law plainly require it? Nay, Does not our Lord Chriſt declare, That the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was made for Man? <hi>Mark. 2. ver.</hi> 27. and, Does he not ſay, he is Lord of the <hi>Sabbath? ver.</hi> 28. What, would you Rob Chriſt of his Lordſhip, and give him another for it? It will not be accepted by him, no other is a Type of our Eternal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38017:7"/>
Reſt. (Compare King <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebels</hi> Dealing with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> for his Vineyard to this.) Why ſhould our Lord bid the <hi>Jews</hi> pray, that their Flight be not on the <hi>Sabbath Day</hi> (which was to be near <hi>Forty</hi> Years after) if they were not bound to obſerve the <hi>Sabbath? Mat.</hi> 24. 20. How can our Lord's Word be Fulfilled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 17, 18. if the Sabbath be changed from the Seventh-Day to the Firſt? For, more than one jot or one tittle will paſs from the Law, if the Sabbath Day be changed, which is ſo pointed out by <hi>Notes</hi> of <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> by <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> by <hi>Pronouns,</hi> by <hi>Prepoſitions;</hi> all ſignificant to point out the Seventh Day, as I have ſhewed already. Have a care of Teaching Men to break any one of Chriſt's Commands, or of Erring in one point, <hi>James</hi> 2. 10. If you would have any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Re-inforcing of this Law, than what I have mentioned; pray ſhew me where the Seventh Part of time hath any other Re-inforcing, and yet you aſſert a Seventh Part of time to be Moral, and to be the Law of Chriſt. <hi>How <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilfully</hi> did you open and apply, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 5. One Man eſteems one day above another; another eſteems every day alike; <hi>This you ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the</hi> Seventh-Day-Sabbath, <hi>and that the Apoſtle (by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Chriſt) left Men to their Liberty, to do as they were perſwaded in their own Mind.</hi> What if a Man be perſwaded, the Seventh-Day is the Sabbath? according to your Doctrine, he is to be left to do, as he is perſwaded in his own Mind; and not to be ſet againſt with Frightful words, as if he were departing from the Living God, as your Text was; nor ſet againſt with whole Sermons, that have no Alliance to the Text they are raiſed from. Neither ſhould a Man of this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be ſlandered, as if he fell into an Error, that had many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Errors attend it? No, he ſhould be left to do, as he is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his own mind. What if a Man eſteems every day alike, and Works every day, and keeps no Sabbath; or Idles every day, and does no Work? By your Doctrine he muſt be left to his perſwaſion. You went to contradict your ſelf, by bringing another caſe, which would no wayes agree, nor run<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paralell with it; that of Chriſt's ſaying to the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> about <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and that Mountain, not being the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Worſhip, <hi>Whence you Argued, every place is alike, a place of Worſhip,</hi> which has no footing in that Scripture; but I will let that paſs, to ſhew you how Unskilfully you Argued from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38017:8"/>
thence; for if all places were alike places of Worſhip; yet that does not leave Men to their own perſwaſions, whether to Worſhip or not: No, our Lord tells us, The Father ſeeks true Spiritual Worſhipers; ſo that Worſhip is ſtill required there; and if you would have any inference from this, it muſt be; then Men may Worſhip where they will; as to the place, if it be indifferent, then in the Idols Temple, or where Men have a mind. This is the moſt you can get by this Unskilful Compariſon. O but you added, <hi>We were freed from</hi> Moſes <hi>his Yoak, and were to take Chriſt's Yoak upon us:</hi> Are we? then we muſt not walk after our own perſwaſions; and if we are to take Chriſt's Yoak upon us, then we are to keep his Sabbath, that plain pleaſant Way of his, and to call it our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he will multiply Bleſſings upon us.</p>
            <p>Thus I have been helped, to throw down your ſtrong hold in which you truſted. Yet for fear this ſhould fail, you brought another from the conſtant practiſe of the Apoſtles, who you ſaid ſlighted the Seventh-Day, and met upon the Firſt: Tremble at the VVord of the Lord which gives the lye to your Aſſertion, <hi>Acts,</hi> 14. 13. - 44. and 16. 13. and 17. 2, 3. and 18. 4. and if you will prove the Apoſtles met on the firſt day of the week, for Inſtituted VVorſhip, firſt tell me, whether in <hi>Matt. 28. 1. Mark. 16. 2. Luke 24. 1. John 20. 1. 19. Acts</hi> 20. 7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. that which is Rendred the Firſt day of the week, be not in every one of thoſe places one of the Sabbaths; and if ſo, what thoſe Sabbaths are; and whether then you will find any ground to bottom your Aſſertion upon, that the Apoſtles met on the firſt day for Inſtituted VVorſhip? You alſo had a third Argument from <hi>Revel. 1. 10. I was in the Spirit on the Lords Day,</hi> which you would have to be the firſt day of the week; but gave not one Scripture for your Interpretation. VVhat muſt it be taken for granted upon your ſaying? But I will offer Scripture and Argument againſt that Interpretation. Did you not acknowledge the Seventh-Day is call'd the Sabbath of the Lord, and the Lords Holy Day; and doth not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſay he is <hi>Lord of the Sabbath-Day;</hi> ſo that if it meant any one particular day in the week, it muſt be this Seventh-Day-Sabbath, and this is a ſolid ground ſo to judg. But I think it is no ingenious Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the place, to limit it to any particular day in the week; for <hi>John</hi> ſaw in Viſions, and heard by Voice, all thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38017:8"/>
things that are Revealed in that book, and was Removed from place to place, a work too great to be concluded to be done in one natural day, unleſs you had clearer Evidence that it was ſo; But doth not this day evidently relate to that providential day of the Lord Chriſts Appearing in the fulfilling of this Propheſie; for this manifeſtation by Viſion and by Voice to <hi>John,</hi> was, as if the thing had been acted and performed before his Face, as if the day of the performance of thoſe Propheſies had been come: He was ſo in that day in the Spirit, that it was to him made Real, and that not only to Faith but to outward Sences, and this providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial day has many dayes and years in it. Now you are Retired from your task in the Pulpit, do you not ſee how like a drowning man you caught at every ſtraw to uphold your Cauſe; but it ſinks and falls before Chriſt's triumphant VVord.</p>
            <p>But here is one broken Reed more you had to lean upon, your Fourth Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſaid the Promiſes to the Obſervers of the Seventh-Day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and threatnings againſt the Tranſgreſſors of it, were transferred to the Firſt-Day.</hi> But how did you go to prove it, not by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is profitable for Doctrine; but by Experience (O ſaid you) <hi>Who are the People that are bleſſed in ſoul and in body and eſtate; but the conſcientious Obſervers of the Firſt-Day.</hi> But pray Sir, conſider, Did not the Lord manifeſt himſelf once and again to <hi>Solomon</hi> at the High Place, and bleſs him in ſoul, body, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and all? Should he therefore conclude and ſay, The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is transferred from the place of Inſtituted VVorſhip to the forbidden High-Place; and therfore that is to be gone to; when there is an expreſs word of the Lord tranſgreſſed in ſo doing. (if the Lord ſhould not over-look ſins in his People, when would he ever manifeſt himſelf to them) and for the judgments inflicted on thoſe who had a conſcience of ſin in the prophaning the day, and yet dareingly did it; there is no Argument in it; nay, you make the ſame thing an Argument againſt the Seventh-Day-Sabbath; for (ſaid you) <hi>If the Seventh-Day-Sabbath be Obſerved, then the penalty againſt Transgreſſors muſt be obſerved. Then</hi> (ſaid you) <hi>we ſhould have ſtoneing work in our ſtreets.</hi> When as you had but one Scripture-inſtance of the executing the penalty on the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the Law of the Sabbath, and it was done at the Word of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Judgment was the Lords, it ſhould make you fear to offend and not fear to obey. And though that be ſuch a Bug-bear
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38017:9"/>
to fright off your Hearers from the Seventh-Day-Sabbath; yet you ſay, <hi>the transferring the Penalty from the Seventh Day to the Firſt,</hi> is an Argument for the firſt-day being the Sabbath: But to let your Argument run upon its own feet, it will be thus, That Sabbath-day that has ſuch a penalty Annexed to it, is not to be owned under the Goſpel; but the penalty annexed to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day, is transferred to the firſt day: Therefore the firſt-day is not to be owned for a Sabbath under the Goſpel. Is not this your Poſition, and the natural Conſequence? Does it not turn upon you?</p>
            <p>But I will not let you have the laſt word, therefore I will add this farther: Does not the Scripture Record the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of tranſgreſſors of the reſt of the Commands? muſt they therefore be Rejected? will you ſtand it out againſt the Lord, to eſcape his ſtroaks? It will be hard for you to kick againſt the Goads: Therefore cloſe in with him, by timely Repentance; and lay hold of his ſtrength, and make peace with Him, and you ſhall make peace with Him. The Lord will not be trifled with, neither do I trifle with you: unleſs you give me a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Reply by Letter, or Anſwer my Objections one way or other, the next Firſt-day; you may Expect I will take ſome other Method to make my Objections known to your Hearers.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Houſe in <hi>Eaſt-Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Hart,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>2d.</hi> Month <hi>23d.</hi> at Evening. 82.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Tovey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIT.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>14th</hi> of the <hi>3d.</hi> Month in the Morning, I cauſed ſeveral of theſe Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be given to Mr. <hi>Meads</hi> Hearers; but when he came to Preach in the Afternoon, I hear he took no Notice of my Arguments, but uſed ſeveral <hi>Raileries;</hi> And <hi>Paraphraſing</hi> upon my Trade, ſaid, <hi>I call'd my ſelf Gold Smith, but my Gold was Copper.</hi> But (although I did not call my ſelf Gold-Smith to him, yet that is my Calling, and my Gold is Standard) if it were Copper, why did he not lay it to the Touch-ſtone of the Word, and make it Manifeſt? For, There things will appear in their true Colours. No— he would be excuſed from that Task, becauſe I would not let <hi>Him</hi> have the laſt word in <hi>My</hi> Letter: But I think he is better skilled at Scoffing, than at trying Doctrines by the Word; elſe, Why did he uſe that old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Who ſo bold, as blind</hi> Bayard? But I ſeriouſly commend that Old Scripture to his conſideraiton, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 18, to the end, —<hi>Who Blind, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Servant? or Deaf, as my Meſſenger?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
